A Finding Aid to the Jacques Lipchitz papers and Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1910-2001, bulk 1941-2001, in the Archives of American Art AAA.lipcjacq2
Archives of American Art
- Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1961-2001; Series 2; 43.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-67, OV 68-69
  - Business Records, 1968-2001; 2.2; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-14
    - Histor Systems, 1991-2001; 2.2.2
      The last installation of the interactive system to be documented here was with the exhibition Lipchitz and the Avant-Garde: From Paris to New York, in 2001 at Krannert Art Museum, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Krannert Art Museum records relate to the financial and logistical operation of the interactive system, as well as marketing and publicity for the exhibition.
      Subseries 2.5, Film projects related to Jacques Lipchitz, contains the actual audiovisual content of the interactive project and the Lipchitz documentary, as well as records related to their production.
      - Interactive Project File, 1991-1997 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - Documentary Subtitle Records, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 20-21)
      - Financial Records, 1997-2000 (Box 13, Folder 22-24)
      - Israel Demonstration Files, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 25)
      - Krannert Art Museum (Box 14)
        - Staffing Invoices, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 1)
        - Marketing, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 2-4)
        - Guest Log, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 5)
        - Visitor Response, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 6)
        - Staffing for Interactive Program, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 7)
        - Hanno Mott Correspondence, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 8)
        - Calendar, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 9)
        - Publicity, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 10)
        - Publicity Photographs, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 11)
          (Contains photographs of Bassett with Jacques Lipchitz)
        - Gertrude Stein Performance at Members' Reception, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Printed Materials, 1961-2001; 2.3; 0.6 Linear feet Box 14, OV 68
    This subseries contains published material on Lipchitz collected by Bassett, as well as publicity for Bassett's Lipchitz documentary and interactive projects. A.M. Hammacher's book Lipchitz is inscribed by Jacques Lipchitz.
    - Articles about Lipchitz (1942-1997), undated; 2 Folders Photocopies (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
    - Internet Printouts about Lipchitz, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Book Research, circa 1968-2001 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Lipcthiz Obituaries, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Jacques Lipchitz: Mother and Child, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Lipchitz by A.M. Hammacher, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - The Artist at Work: Jacques Lipchitz, Master Sculptor, Encyclopedia Brittanica Educational Corporation, 1968; (1 film reel) (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art Exhibition Poster, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 21)
      Oversized item housed in OV 68
    - Publicity, Lipchitz Documentary, 1974-1978 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Publicity, Lipchitz Interactive Project, 1972-2001 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Oversized Exhibition Poster (Oversized material from Box 14, F21) (Box OV 68)
    - Oversized Publicity, Lipchitz Documentary (Oversized material from Box 14, F22) (Box OV 68)
  - Interview with Jacques Lipchitz conducted by Deborah Stott, 1968-1970; 2.4; 8 Linear feet Boxes 14-22
    Deborah Stott, at the time a graduate student in Art History at Columbia University, recorded roughly 200 hours of conversation with the artist between 1968 and 1970 in Pietrasanta, Italy. The series contains a near-complete run of the sound recordings on 209 sound tape reels (1/4"), as well as detailed typewritten summaries of the subject content for each reel are available at the beginning of the series, and a 32 page transcript of the first reel. 183 of the reels are marked "first dub" and are presumably copies made from the original tape. 26 of the original sound reels are also found, for tape numbers 112-135 and 184-185, and are interfiled with their dubbed copies. Reels 137 and 165 are not extant, but typewritten summaries do exist for those reels. Also found are photographs that document Lipchitz's acquired collection of primitive and ancient art, which are often referred to by number in the interviews. Included are contact sheets, negatives, prints, and photocopies of prints.
    This interview was carried out under the auspices of the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation and largely funded by a grant from the Ford Foundation.
    Some of the sound recordings have been digitized for research access.
    - Summaries and Transcript, 1968 July 31-1970 March 27; 5 Folders (Box 14, Folder 24-28)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 1-36, 1968 July 31-1968 September 27; (36 sound tape reels) (Box 15, Item 1-36)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 37-72, 1968 Sept. 28-1968 Dec. 4; (36 sound tape reels) (Box 16, Item 1-36)
    - Sound recordings, Reels 73-108, 1968 Dec. 4-1969 July 28; (36 sound tape reels) (Box 17, Item 1-36)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 109-128, 1969 July 29-1969 Aug. 27; (37 sound tape reels) (Box 18, Item 1-19)
      (includes original reels for #112-128)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 129-136, 138-158, 1969 Aug 28-1970 Jan. 13; (36 sound tape reels) (Box 19, Item 1-29)
      (includes original reels for #129-135)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 159-164, 166-185, 1970 Jan. 13-1970 Mar. 27; (28 sound tape reels) (Box 20, Item 1-26)
      (includes original reels for #184-185)
    - Photographs of Jacques Lipchitz's Acquired Collection (Box 20)
      - Contact Sheets and Negatives, #1-1540, circa 1968; (3 of 4 folders) (Box 20, Folder 27-29)
      - Contact Sheets and Negatives, #1-1540, circa 1968; (1 of 4 folders) (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Contact Sheets and Negatives, #1541-2889, circa 1968; 4 Folders (Box 21, Folder 2-5)
      - Prints, #1-499, circa 1968; 4 Folders Photocopies (Box 21, Folder 6-9)
      - Prints, #500-999, circa 1968; 2 Folders Photocopies (Box 21, Folder 10-11)
      - Prints, #1000-1499, circa 1968; 5 Folders (Box 21, Folder 12-16)
    - Photographs of Jacques Lipchitz's Acquired Collection (Box 22)
      - Prints, #1500-1999, circa 1968; 5 Folders (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
      - Prints, #2500-2889, circa 1968; 5 Folders (Box 22, Folder 6-10)
  - Film Projects Regarding Jacques Lipchitz, 1971-2001; 2.5; 28.2 Linear feet Boxes 22-46, 53-65, OV 69
    This subseries contains paper records, artifacts, motion picture film, video, and sound recordings created and used in the production of Bruce Bassett's film projects related to Jacques Lipchitz. Bassett originally shot over 40 hours of motion picture film with synchronized sound recordings in 1971. From this footage he developed the first incarnations of his two main projects: the Jacques Lipcthiz interactive project, also known as "Conversations with Jacques Lipchitz," and a documentary about Lipchitz. Both projects debuted to the public at the 1972 Jacques Lipcthiz retrospective exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City. After Lipchitz's death in 1974, Bassett shot additional footage documenting the casting of large-scale Lipchitz sculptures in Italy, and the installations of those sculptures in New York, Philadelphia, and Jerusalem, carried out by his widow, Yulla Lipchitz. This material was used in an updated version of the documentary, which was released around 1977. Subsequent releases occurred in the late 1980s and early 1990s. The interactive project was also exhibited in multiple versions, in a variety of formats as video and computer technology evolved, between 1973 and 2001. See the subseries descriptions below for more detail.
    The series is arranged as 3 subseries:
    2.5.1: Original Footage and Stock Footage, 1971-1981
    2.5.2: Jacques Lipchitz Interactive Project, 1972-2001
    2.5.3: Jacques Lipchitz Documentary, 1972-1994
    - Original Footage and Stock Footage, 1971-1981; 2.5.1
      This subseries contains original footage shot by Bassett and his crew and used as the source material for his two film projects documenting Jacques Lipchitz. Bassett's initial filming took place in Italy in August and September of 1971, and later in Philadelphia, Miami, New York, and Jerusalem between 1976 And 1978. Footage from the shoot in Italy contains several long interviews with Lipchitz and footage shot in his Italian studio and foundry. All numbered camera and sound reels from the Italy filming are described in detail in the script book at the beginning of the series. Film and sound footage from the later shoots contain mainly documentation of the posthumous large-scale sculpture installations overseen by Lipchitz's widow, Yulla Lipchitz, as well as multiple interviews with her.
      120 of the 171 original sound reels from the Italy filming survive, but very little of the camera footage remains. In addition to original sound reels, a dubbed copy of all of the sound recorded in Italy is found on a smaller set of reels, so any missing original sound reels can be recovered from the dubbed copy. Four miscellaneous, sound-only reels of original sound recordings are also found. None of the original camera reels remain from the Italy shoot, but workprint copies of 20 of the 193 original camera and sound reels were made at a later stage in Bassett's work, possibly to edit new versions of his film projects. These workprints were named "archival prints" by Bassett and are the only remaining raw footage from the 1971 filming period in Italy. Some of them have splices, indicating portions were removed. Reels are listed by the new reel numbers assigned by Bassett when they were re-printed, but their original reel numbers, indexed and described in the script book at the beginning of the series, are also noted. Two unnumbered reels of original footage of Lipchitz working in his studio on the sculpture The Last Embrace are also found in this series.
      For later filming in the US and Jerusalem, original camera reels, some with sound on film, and separate original sound reels are found. There is no paper record of these shoots in the collection. Material is arranged by subject and date. Other raw footage found includes four camera reels of sculptures by Lipchitz from the Metropolitan Museum.
      Other source material in this series includes stock footage and stock soundtrack, produced by others but used in Bassett's Lipchitz projects, and a couple of short reels of sound effects and titles.
      Note that the workprint is silent 16 mm picture unless otherwise indicated, original sound reels are ¼" tape, and soundtrack is 16mm fullcoat magnetic stock. Some of the later foundry and installation footage was shot on reversal positive film with a magnetic stripe soundtrack, identified in the container listing as sound on film.
      - Italy Filming (Box 22)
        - Script Book, circa 1971, 3 Folders Photocopies (Box 22, Folder 11-13)
        - Sound reels #1-14 and 25-49, 1971 August-September; (38 sound tape reels) (Box 23, Item 1-38)
        - Sound reels #50-71, 73-81, 107, 123-128, 1971; (38 sound tape reels) (Box 24, Item 1-38)
        - Sound Reels #129-166, 1971; (38 sound tape reels) (Box 25, Item 1-38)
        - Sound reels # 167-171, 1971; (5 sound tape reels) (Box 26, Item 1-5)
        - Dubbed sound reels #1-13, circa 1971; (13 sound tape reels) (Box 26, Item 6-18)
          (A key to original reels contained on each dub reel is found with dub reel 1, box 5, item 6.)
        - Interview of Lipchitz by Bruce Bassett, 1971 June 24; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 26, Item 19)
          (A pre-production interview, about the pending Metropolitan Museum exhibition)
        - Lipchitz Interview Re-takes, 1972 April 29; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 26, Item 20)
        - Interview with Jacques Lipchitz, circa 1971; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 26, Item 21)
          (Excerpts)
        - Florence Section Narration, undated; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 26, Item 22)
        - Lipchitz Working in Clay, Sync Sound, undated; (1 sound tape reel) (Box 26, Item 23)
        - Archival Reel 31, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 1)
          (Original camera reel 137)
        - Archival Reel 32, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 2)
          (Original camera reels 145-146)
        - Archival Reel 33, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 3)
          (Original camera reels 148-150)
        - Archival Reel 34, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 4)
          (Original camera reel 152)
        - Archival Reel 35, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 5)
          (Original camera reel 163)
        - Archival Reel 37, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 6)
          (Original camera reels 181-182)
        - Archival Reel 38, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 7)
          (Original camera reels 184-186)
        - Archival Reel 39, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 8)
          (Original camera reels 187-188)
        - Archival Reel 40, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 27, Item 9)
          (Original camera reels 189-191)
        - Archival Reel 41, circa 1971; (1 film reel: workprint picture) (Box 28, Item 1)
          (Original camera reels 192-193)
        - Archival Reel 31, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 2)
          (original sound reel 131)
        - Archival Reel 32, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 3)
          (Original sound reel 139-140)
        - Archival Reel 33, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 4)
          (Original sound reel 142-144)
        - Archival Reel 35, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 5)
          (Original sound reel 152)
        - Archival Reel 37, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 6)
          (Original sound reels 158-159)
        - Archival Reel 38, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 7)
          (Original sound reels 162, 164)
        - Archival Reel 39, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 8)
          (Original sound reels 166-167)
        - Archival Reel 40, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 28, Item 9)
          (Original sound reels 167-169)
        - Archival Reel 41, circa 1971; (1 film reel: soundtrack) (Box 29, Item 1)
          (Original sound reels 170-171)
        - Lipchitz Working on His Sculpture The Last Embrace, circa 1972; (2 film reels: picture) (Box 29, Item 2)
      - Lipchitz Sculpture at the Metropolitan Museum, 1972; 4 film reels: picture; 2 oversized reels in Box 53) (Box 29, Item 3)
      - Index to Sculptures Filmed at the Metropolitan Museum, undated (Box 29, Item 4)
        Index on paper, 1 folder
      - Selected Sculptures, European Shoot, undated; (1 videocassette: U-Matic) (Box 29, Item 5)
      - Philadelphia Installation and Dedication of Government of the People, 1976-1977; (16 film reels: picture, 2 film reels: sound on film, and 1 sound tape reel; film housed in 4 film cans, 2 oversized film cans in Box 54) (Box 29, Item 6)
      - New York Installation of Bellerophon Taming Pegasus, 1977 April; (8 film reels: sound on film, 1 film reel: picture, 8 sound tape reels, 1 duplicate videocassette: U-Matic; film housed in 2 oversized film cans in Box 55) (Box 30, Item 1)
      - Interview with Yulla Lipchitz, 1977 May; (5 film reels: picture; film housed in 2 film cans, 1 oversized film can in box 44) (Box 30, Item 2)
        Picture only, no sound
      - Italian Foundry Filming, 1977 August; (1 film reel: sound on film) (Box 30, Item 3)
      - Miami Interview with Joe Harrison, 1977; (1 film reel, 1 sound tape reel) (Box 30, Item 4)
        (See also series 5.2, Segments)
      - Israel Filming, 1977-1978; (8 film reels: picture, 1 film reel: sound on film; film housed in 2 film cans, 1 oversized film can in Box 56) (Box 30, Item 5)
      - Unidentified Aerial Footage, undated; (1 film reel) (Box 30, Item 6)
      - Sound Effects and Titles, undated; (9 film reels: 35mm magnetic sound loop, 1 film reel: 16mm magnetic sound loop, 2 film reels: 35mm picture; film housed in 1 film can) (Box 30, Item 7)
      - Stills and Animation, undated; (5 film reels in 1 film can) (Box 30, Item 8)
      - Stock Footage, undated; (6 film reels in 1 film can) (Box 30, Item 9)
      - Oversized Reels of Original Footage, Lipchitz Sculpture at the Metropolitan Museum (Oversized material from Box 29, item 3) (Box 53)
      - Oversized Film Cans of Original Footage, Philadelphia Installation (Oversized material from Box 29, item 6) (Box 54)
      - Oversized Film Cans of Original Footage, New York Installation (Oversized material from Box 30, item 1) (Box 55)
      - Oversized Film Cans of Original Footage, Yulla Lipchitz Interview and Israel Filming (Oversized material from Box 30, items 2 and 5) (Box 56)
    - Jacques Lipchitz Interactive Project, 1972-2001; 2.5.2
      This subseries contains the edited film and video created for the Lipchitz interactive project, as well as paper records documenting the production and presentation of its various installations.
      Audiovisual materials include multiple versions of "answers" compiled from the Lipchitz interviews filmed in 1971, used in multiple interactive installations between 1972 and 2001. Each version exists in a group of 2 to 4 reels or tapes, in its source format of motion picture film, or its installation format of various video types. Each group and its elements is described using the reel names and numbers assigned by Bassett to maintain their connection to paper documentation, and groups are arranged chronologically. The item headings listed below are direct transcriptions of Bassett's labels. Six miscellaneous reels, which do not appear to belong to any of the main groups of film reels, are arranged after the dated reels. Although they may duplicate some of the dated material, these miscellaneous reels were found to be in better condition than some of their copies, so they were retained.
      Also found are 117 small film and soundtrack reels of named segments whose titles correspond to segments listed in the source books. These may be outtakes or workprint of the edited Lipchitz answers.
      Paper records in this series include the original questions generated by the public during installations of the interactive project. Questions exist in multiple forms including orignal handwritten cards and printouts in multiple sets, each with a different arrangement of data. Notebooks include mainly technical and shot notes, but also notes on an Andy Goldsworthy interview. Production files contain detailed notes on the assembly of segments and revisions to the reels, including a negative pull list for a recent revision. The Program Guide contains annotated indexes to segments on each reel or disc, and other technical notes.
      Source Books, found in the paper documentation, provide a scene-by-scene content inventory and transcript of the audiovisual material in each version presented to the public between 1972 and 2001. They also contain notes related to the operation of the interactive program. Although all of the source books contain redundant and similar content, each version has its own annotations and a variety of interfiled production records specific to its particular installation. The 2001 source book from the Krannert Art Museum installation also includes a disc directory, photographs of sculptures in the Krannert exhibit, and an article on Lipchitz.
      Technical drawings show the way the video equipment was set up in the installations, showing a user in relation to the interactive system display. The Transcript folder includes a collection of Lipchitz's comments on Pablo Picasso gathered from the footage, a portion of which appears to have been licensed to another production company in the 1980s.
      The chronological arrangement of audiovisual materials in this series has been altered slightly due to the size and physical requirements of the objects.
      - Audiovisual Materials (Box 31)
        - Introduction, circa 1972; (2 film reels: workprint and soundtrack; oversized workprint in Box 57, oversized soundtrack in Box 58) (Box 31, Item 1)
        - Birth-Cubism, circa 1972; (2 film reels: workprint and soundtrack; oversized workprint in Box 57, oversized soundtrack in Box 58) (Box 31, Item 2)
        - Transparencies-Jacob and the Angel, circa 1972; (2 film reels: workprint and soundtrack; oversized soundtrack in Box 58, oversized workprint in Box 59) (Box 31, Item 3)
        - Mother-Virgin, circa 1972; (2 film reels: workprint and soundtrack; oversized workprint in Box 59, oversized soundtrack in Box 60) (Box 31, Item 4)
        - Reel A, Part 1, 1972; (2 film reels: A+B roll, 1 sound tape reel) (Box 31, Item 5)
        - Reel A, Part 2, 1972; (2 film reels: A+B roll, 1 sound tape reel) (Box 31, Item 6)
        - Reel B, Part 1, 1972; (2 film reels: A+B roll, 1 sound tape reel) (Box 31, Item 7)
        - Reel B, Part 2, 1972; undated; (2 film reels: A+B roll, 1 sound tape reel) (Box 31, Item 8)
        - Unidentified Reel, 1972; (2 film reels: A+B roll) (Box 32, Item 1)
        - Reel D, 1979; (2 videocassettes: U-Matic, 1 with visible time code) (Box 32, Item 2)
        - Reels A-D, 1979; (4 videocassettes: Betacam SP) (Box 33, Item 1)
        - Discs I-II, circa 1982; (2 videocassettes: U-Matic) (Box 33, Item 2)
        - Discs I-IV, 1999; (4 videocassettes: Digital Betacam) (Box 33, Item 3)
        - Reel A, 1982; (2 film reels: workprint, 2 film reels: soundtrack) (Box 34, Item 1)
        - Reel B, 1982; (2 film reels: workprint, 2 film reels: soundtrack) (Box 34, Item 2)
        - Reel C, 1982; (1 film reel: workprint, 1 film reel: soundtrack; oversized workprint in Box 61, oversized soundtrack reel in Box 60) (Box 34, Item 3)
        - Reel D, 1982; (1 film reel: workrpint, 1 film reel: soundtrack; oversized workrpint in Box 61, oversized soundtrack reel in Box 60) (Box 34, Item 4)
        - Miscellaneous Reels (Box 35)
          - Monitor Station Segments, undated; (2 film reels: internegative and answer print, 1 sound tape reel) (Box 35, Item 1)
          - Met, undated; (2 film reels: workprint and sountrack) (Box 35, Item 2)
          - Reel C, Part 1, undated; (1 film reel: workprint) (Box 35, Item 3)
            (Note on original can: "does not contain Picasso")
          - Q+A Reel C, 1971; (1 film reel: picture, oversized reel in Box 62) (Box B35B23, Item 4)
          - Reel II, Part 1, undated; (1 film reel: picture, oversized reel in Box 62) (Box 35, Item 5)
            (Leader also labeled "D Reel")
          - Unidentified Reel, undated; (1 film reel: workprint) (Box 35, Item 6)
        - Segments (Box 35)
          - Art Is Eternal, Banker's Economy, Bellerophon, circa 1971-1981; (4 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 35, Item 7)
          - Bellerophon, circa 1971-1981; (6 film reels: workprint, in 2 film cans) (Box 35, Item 8)
          - Birth and Unity, circa 1971-1981; (3 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 36, Item 1)
          - Columbine, circa 1971-1981; (2 film reels: workprint, in 1 oversized film can in Box 63) (Box 36, Item 2)
          - Cubism, End Section, FF, First Come to America, Florence, Freeze, Government of the People, circa 1971-1981; (7 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 36, Item 3)
          - Government of the People, circa 1971-1981; (3 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 36, Item 4)
          - Gursenski, James Joyce, circa 1971-1981; (4 film reels: workprint) (Box 36, Item 5)
          - Last Embrace, circa 1971-1981; (4 film reels: workprint, in 1 oversized film can in Box 63) (Box 36, Item 6)
          - Man Getting Better, Miami and Joe Harrison Interview, circa 1971-1981; (4 film reels: workprint, in 1 film can) (Box 36, Item 7)